A Guide to the Papers of Dr. John Kern 1986-2011
Roanoke Public Libraries
Roanoke Public Libraries
A Guide to the Papers of Dr. John Kern
Roanoke Public Libraries
2010.1.04
4 record storage boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Dr. John Kern
Biographical Note
John Kern was born on January 28, 1940 in Iowa City, Iowa. After earning his bachelor’s degree at Swarthmore College in 1961, he served two years in the Peace Corps in Tunisia. He earned his master’s degree from the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 1968, and he became interested in black history while earning his doctoral degree in American history at the same institution in 1976. He came to Roanoke in 1989 to become the regional director of Virginia’s newly created Department of Historic Resources. The office nominated many Southwest Virginia historic sites and areas to state and national registries. Some of his accomplishments include the successful nomination of the Historic Gainsboro District to the National Register of Historic Places in 2005 and the placement of the Pearisburg Downtown Historic District on the Virginia Landmarks Register and the National Register of Historic Places. He taught courses in black history at Hollins University until 2008. He has published work in Dictionary of Virginia Biography, Florida Memorial College Academic Review, Notes on Virginia, From Here to There, and Delaware History. One of his former Hollins students, Arleen Ollie, said of Kern, “John is much like one of the treasures he has resurrected.” He was called “a fervent steward of history” by The Roanoke Times. Kern retired from the Department of Historic Resources in 2010. He received an Education Award from the Roanoke Valley Preservation Society in the same year.
Scope and Content
The Kern Papers are comprised of documents, photographs, and newspaper articles that are a product of the research done by Kern during his time as Roanoke Regional Director for the Virginia Department of Historic Resources at the Department of Historic Resources. The collection includes copies of nominations of historic sites in Southwest Virginia to the National Registry of Historic Places and the research that went into those nominations, including records, photographs, and newspaper articles. Also included in Kern’s papers is his research of several areas in Southwest Virginia, including sites in Roanoke, Henry, Montgomery, Pulaski, Rockbridge, Smyth, Franklin, Floyd, Washington, Giles, and Russell Counties as well as in Roanoke City, Blacksburg, Wytheville, Buena Vista, and Covington, that were not nominated, research on Robert J. Boland and John Willis Chappelear, Jr, that were submitted to the Dictionary of Virginia Biography series, articles and research on subjects related to black history in Southwest Virginia, and documents related to workshops and conferences on black history that Kern helped organize. Research and a paper done under Kern’s supervision by an intern on Roanoke’s segregation ordinances is included as well. Many of the reports and nominations included can also be accessed online at www.dhr.virginia.gov.
Arrangement
Documents are arranged roughly by geographical location.
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Research on Buena Vista (Folder 1)
  - Research on Belmont (Folder 2)
  - "Historical, Archaeological and Architectural Investigations of Belmont in the City of Roanoke" (Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Research on William Fleming and Belmont (Folder 4)
  - Map and Tracings of William Fleming's Plantation and land (Folder 5)
  - Belmont Report (Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Research on Belmont (Folder 7)
  - Account Book of William Fleming 1768-1780 (Folder 8)
  - "Thematic Evaluation of County Public School Buildings in Southwest Virginia" (Folder 9)
  - Greenfield in Botetourt County, Virginia 2009 (Folder 10)
  - Greenfield Kitchen and Cabin - Virginia Tech View Shed/Lanscape Analysis 2009 (Folder 11)
  - Research on Robert J. Boland 2001 (Folder 12)
  - From Here to There: "South By Wagon" (Folder 13)
  - Black History in Southwest Virginia - research and article 1994 (Folder 14)
  - George Kegley "Roast" and Biographical Materials (Folder 15)
  - John Willis Chappelear, Jr. Biographical Information 2006 (Folder 16)
  - "Oscar Micheaux, Race Films and Roanoke's Strand Theatre" 2006 (Folder 17)
  - Oscar Micheaux and Gainsboro - Research from Ed Barnett (Folder 18)
  - "Record of Early Family Ownership of Land and Buildings on Gills Creek, Frankin County, Virginia, 1786-1847 (Folder 19)
  - Jubal Early's Homes in Franklin County, Virginia (Folder 20)
  - New Castle Historic District (Folder 21)
  - National Register of Historic Places Nominations: Buchanan, Clifton Forge, Covington, Danville, Dublin, Petersburg, Lylburn Downing School, Philip Craft House, Hill Grove School, Mt. Moriah Baptist Church and Cemetery, Olive Branch Missionary Baptist Church (Folder 22)
  - Mt. Moriah Baptist Church Easement 2004 (Folder 23)
  - Mt. Moriah Baptist Church Easement and Historic Marker 2000 (Folder 24-27)
- Nominations with Research for the National Register of Historic Places; Some nominations partial (Box 2)
  - Childress Presbyterian Rock Churches, Nominations: Buffalo Mountain, Dinwiddie, Mayberry, Willis, Bluemont and Floyd (Folder 1)
  - Childress Presbyterian Rock Churches, Research: Dinwiddie, Buffalo Mountain, Slate Mountain and Bluemont (Folder 2)
  - Childress Presbyterian Rock Churches, Research: Bob Childress, Willis and Miscellaneous (Folder 3)
  - Fieldale Historic District in Franklin County, Nomination (Folder 4)
  - Fieldale Research: 1958 Land Books and Oral History Interviews (Folder 5)
  - Fieldale Research: Miscellaneous (Folder 5)
  - Fieldale Research, Including Maps 2007 (Folder 6)
  - Fieldale Research: Articles by Bea Bullard (Folder 7)
  - Fayette Street Historic District in Martinsville, Nomination (Folder 8)
  - Fayette Street, Research (Folder 10-11)
  - Kentland Farm District in Montgomery County: Historic and Archaeological Nomination (Folder 12)
  - Kentland Farm, Research (Folder 13-16)
  - Kent Family Slaves: Montgomery and Pulaski Counties 2007 (Folder 17)
  - Kentland Background (Folder 18)
  - Gainsboro Library in Roanoke, Nomination (Folder 19)
  - Gainsboro Library, Research (Folder 20)
  - Hotel Roanoke, Nomination (Folder 21)
  - Norfolk and Western Archives (Folder 22)
  - Hotel Roanoke, Research (Folder 23)
  - Roanoke Leader, Newspaper 1882 (Folder 24)
  - Establishment of Norfolk and Western and Roanoke Land Improvement Company 1881-1884 (Folder 25)
  - Buffalo Forge in Rockbridge County, Nomination (Folder 26)
  - Buffalo Forge, Research (Folder 27)
  - H.L. Bonham House in Smyth County, Nomination (Folder 28)
  - H.L. Bonham House, Research (Folder 29-30)
  - St. John's Episcopal Church in Wytheville, Nomination 2000 (Folder 31)
  - St. John's Episcopal Church, Research (Folder 32-33)
- Nominations with Research for the National Register of Historic Places; Some nominations partial (Box 3)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Nomination (Folder 1)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Nomination Drafts and Correspondence (Folder 2)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Records 1990 (Folder 3)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Materials from Church, Includes Photographs (Folder 4)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Materials from Geneva Hale (Folder 5)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Research (Folder 6)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Miscellaneous Records 1890 (Folder 7)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Meeting Minutes April 1892, January 1894-June 1900 (Folder 8)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Meeting Minutes September 1900-January 1906 (Folder 9)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Resolutions 1896-1897 (Folder 10)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Miscellaneous Receipts and Correspondence (Folder 11)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Business Meeting Minutes January 1925-June 1927 (Folder 12)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke, Ledger 1924-1930 (Folder 13)
  - First Baptist Church in Roanoke 1995 (Folder 14)
  - Newport Historic District in Giles County, Nomination (Folder 15)
  - Newport Historic District, Research (Folder 16-17)
  - Rocky Mount Historic District in Franklin County, Nomination (Folder 18)
  - Rocky Mount Historic District, Research (Folder 19)
  - Odd Fellows Hall in Blacksburg, Nomination (Folder 20)
  - Odd Fellows Hall in Blacksburg, Research 2005 (Folder 21)
  - Odd Fellows Hall in Blacksburg, Research (Folder 22)
  - Covington High School, Nomination (Folder 23)
  - Covington High School, Research (Folder 24)
  - Jessee's Mill in Russell County, Nomination (Folder 25)
  - Jessee's Mill in Russell County, Research (Folder 26)
  - Piedmont Hill Historic District in Franklin County, Nomination (Folder 27)
  - Piedmont Hill Historic District in Franklin County, Research (Folder 28)
  - Honaker Historic District in Russell County, Nomination (Folder 29)
  - Honaker Historic District in Russell County, Research (Folder 30)
  - W.N. Seay House in Buena Vista, Nomination (Folder 31)
  - W.N. Seay House in Buena Vista, Research (Folder 32)
  - Edmondson Hall in Washington County, Nomination (Folder 33)
  - Edmondson Hall in Washington County, Research (Folder 34)
- (Box 4)
  - Dublin Historic District in Pulaski County, Nomination 1992 (Folder 1)
  - Dublin Historic District in Pulaski County, Research (Folder 2)
  - Floyd Historic District, Nomination (Folder 3)
  - Floyd Research: (Folder 4)
  - Floyd Research: Acts, Census Records, Land Books and Maps (Folder 5)
  - Floyd Research: Schools (Folder 6)
  - Floyd Research: Walking Tour (Folder 7)
  - Floyd Research: Survey and Town Designation, 1986 Comprehensive Plan (Folder 8)
  - Floyd Research: Historical Society Tour 23 June 2004 (Folder 9)
  - Floyd Research: Population and Inventory of Building in the Town of Floyd 1987-1988 (Folder 10)
  - Floyd Research: Internet and Bibliography, Index of Enrolled Bills to 1910 (Folder 11)
  - Floyd Research: Tise Collection Information on Presley Church, Schools and Academies (Folder 12)
  - Floyd Research: Statement of Significance for Floyd Presbyterian Church, Glenanna, Old Court House and Rakes House (Folder 13)
  - Floyd Research: 1986-1989 Comprehensive Plan and News Clippings (Folder 14)
  - Low Moor Mine in Alleghany County, Research (Folder 15-16)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Examples of Primary Research Nominations for Lylburn School, Buffalo Forge and First Baptist Church (Folder 17)
  - 'Segregation by Custom versus Segregation by Law: Residential Segregation Ordinances and their Effects on the City of Roanoke, 1910-1917' by Naomi Mattos 2005 (Folder 18)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Edwards (Folder 19)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Pentecost/Hill (Folder 20)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Dudley (Folder 21)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Roberts (Folder 22)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Residential Law (Folder 23)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Gilmer Avenue (Folder 24)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Black Secret and Professional Societies (Folder 25)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Gainsboro Library (Folder 26)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Oliver White Hill Foundation, Inc. (Folder 27)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Henry Street Historic District (Folder 28)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research: Miscellaneous (Folder 29)
  - Roanoke Segregation Ordinance Research (Folder 30)
  - National Park Service Diversity Intern Program November 2004 (Folder 31-33)
  - Arleen Ollie Grant Proposal (Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Black History Files (Folder 35-38)
  - 'Washington and DuBois at the Turn of Two Centuries': Conference March 1998 (Folder 39)
  - 'African American Heritage Education': Lecture and Workshop 1994 (Folder 40-41)
  - 'African American Heritage Education': List of Registrants and Evaluation Forms 1994 (Folder 42)
  - 'African American Heritage Education': Press and Miscellaneous 1994 (Folder 43)
  - 'African American Heritage Education': Meeting January 1994 (Folder 44)
  - 'Building Codes and Historic Preservation': Workshop (Folder 45)
  - Henry County: Martinsville and Bassett Historic Contexts 1990 (Folder 46)
  - Original Newspapers from Files (Folder 47)
  - 'Davis vs. Prince Edward County, Virginia 1951: Land Book Research on Co-signers on Moton School Student Petitioners': Presented at Virginia Forum 25 March 2011 (Folder 48)
  - 'Bassett Furniture Historic Context, Henry County, Virginia' (Folder 49)
  - Reverend Richard R. Jones Biographical Information (Folder 50)